<models>
  <intro>
    <paragraph>The Greenhouse for Mental Health Development models are conceptual and computational frameworks designed to explore how mental health emerges from the interaction of biological, neurological, behavioral, and environmental systems. Rather than treating mental health as a static condition, these models represent it as a dynamic, adaptive process shaped by feedback loops, learning, stressors, resilience, and recovery.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>Each model isolates a specific layer of human functioning—genetic predisposition, neural signaling, behavioral pathways, and synaptic communication—while remaining interoperable with the others. Together, they form a unified simulation environment for understanding how micro-level processes scale into macro-level mental and emotional outcomes.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>These models are not diagnostic tools. They are educational, exploratory, and research-informed representations meant to promote systems thinking, reduce stigma, and improve public understanding of mental health as a living, evolving process.</paragraph>
  </intro>

  <model id="genetic">
    <title>Genetic Model</title>
    <url>/genetic</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Genetic Model represents inherited predispositions and long-term biological factors that influence mental health outcomes. It does not imply determinism. Instead, it reflects how genetic tendencies interact with environment, stress exposure, learning, and neuroplasticity over time.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This model includes probabilistic traits rather than fixed outcomes. Variables such as emotional sensitivity, stress reactivity, baseline neurotransmitter production, and cognitive flexibility are represented as dynamic ranges rather than binary states. This emphasizes that genetics shape tendencies, not destinies.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Within the simulation framework, the Genetic Model serves as a foundational layer. It establishes initial conditions that affect how other systems—such as neural signaling and behavioral pathways—respond to stimuli. For example, two simulated individuals exposed to the same stressor may experience different emotional trajectories based on genetic variability.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>By modeling genetics as a flexible, interactive system, this framework promotes a more compassionate and scientifically grounded understanding of mental health, helping users move away from blame-based or reductionist explanations.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="neuro">
    <title>Neuro Model</title>
    <url>/neuro</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Neuro Model focuses on how mental states arise from patterns of neural activation, inhibition, and adaptation. Rather than simulating individual neurons in a literal biological sense, this model represents functional brain regions as interacting systems that process emotion, memory, perception, and executive control.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Each region operates as a node in a larger network, exchanging signals that influence mood, attention, threat detection, reward anticipation, and learning. These nodes adapt over time, reflecting principles of neuroplasticity—changes in responsiveness based on experience and repetition.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This model illustrates how mental health is not simply a matter of “chemical imbalance,” but of network dynamics. Overactivation, underactivation, or rigid feedback loops can lead to maladaptive patterns such as rumination, hypervigilance, or emotional shutdown.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The Neuro Model allows users to explore how interventions—such as rest, therapy, reframing, or environmental change—can gradually reshape neural behavior through repeated corrective signaling.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="pathway">
    <title>Pathway Model</title>
    <url>/pathway</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Pathway Model represents behavioral and cognitive habit loops—how thoughts, emotions, and actions reinforce each other over time. These pathways are shaped through repetition, emotional salience, and survival-driven learning.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Instead of labeling behaviors as “good” or “bad,” this model frames them as adaptive responses that once served a purpose. For example, avoidance, emotional numbing, or hypercontrol may have emerged as protective strategies under past conditions.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Over time, these patterns can become rigid, even when they no longer serve the individual’s well-being. The Pathway Model visualizes this rigidity as deeply carved routes that require energy and intention to redirect.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This model emphasizes that growth does not mean erasing the past—it means creating new, healthier routes that gradually become easier to traverse. Change is represented as gradual, not instant, reinforcing realistic expectations for mental health progress.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="synapse">
    <title>Synapse Model</title>
    <url>/synapse</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Synapse Model simulates how meaning, emotion, and memory are transmitted between mental systems. It focuses on how signals are weighted, amplified, dampened, or distorted as they travel through the mind.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>In biological terms, synapses determine the strength of communication between neurons. In this conceptual model, synapses represent how strongly one mental state influences another—such as how fear impacts decision-making, or how hope shapes future planning.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This model illustrates how repeated experiences strengthen certain signal routes while weakening others. Trauma, for example, may amplify threat signals while suppressing reward signals. Healing experiences can rebalance these pathways.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The Synapse Model provides insight into why emotional responses can feel automatic and difficult to override—and how intentional practices can slowly recalibrate those internal weights.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="dopamine">
    <title>Dopamine Signaling Model</title>
    <url>/dopamine</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Dopamine Signaling Model explores the complex dynamics of reward, motivation, and motor control. It simulates the interaction between dopamine molecules and various receptor subtypes, illustrating how these signals translate into cellular responses and influence behavioral patterns.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This model highlights the multi-scale nature of dopaminergic transmission—from the immediate kinetics of receptor binding to the long-term effects on synaptic plasticity and circuit-level behavior. By visualizing these processes, the model provides insight into the biological foundations of drive and reinforcement.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="serotonin">
    <title>Serotonin Structural Model</title>
    <url>/serotonin</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Serotonin Structural Model provides a detailed visualization of the 5-HT1A receptor and its interactions with ligands. This simulation highlights the structural biology of serotonergic signaling, focusing on how molecular binding events influence mood regulation and emotional stability.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>By modeling the 7-transmembrane architecture and the precise transport mechanisms of serotonin, this framework allows users to explore the fundamental biological processes that underpin emotional equilibrium and resilience. It emphasizes the critical link between molecular integrity and mental well-being.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="dna">
    <title>DNA Repair Model</title>
    <url>/dna</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The DNA Repair Model provides a horizontal molecular visualization of key biological pathways that maintain genomic integrity. This interactive simulation allows users to explore mechanisms such as Base Excision Repair (BER), Mismatch Repair (MMR), and Double-Strand Break (DSB) repair.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>By visualizing these micro-level processes, the model emphasizes the fundamental biological resilience and constant adaptive maintenance required for life and mental health development.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="rna">
    <title>RNA Repair Model</title>
    <url>/rna</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The RNA Repair Model features a vertical molecular visualization of the mechanisms that protect and repair RNA transcripts. It highlights specialized pathways like RNA Ligation and Oxidative Demethylation, which are crucial for maintaining the fidelity of protein synthesis.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This simulation helps users understand the linear nature of long RNA transcripts and the specialized enzymes, such as AlkB, that ensure cellular information remains accurate and functional.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="emotion">
    <title>Emotion Model</title>
    <url>/emotion</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Emotion Model explores the neurological foundations of human affect, focusing on the Limbic System—a complex set of structures including the amygdala, hippocampus, and hypothalamus. This model visualizes how emotional states are not just feelings, but physiological events triggered by sensory input and modulated by cognitive appraisal.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>By integrating classical psychological theories such as James-Lange, Cannon-Bard, and Schachter-Singer, the simulation illustrates the dynamic interplay between bodily responses and mental interpretation. It highlights how the brain detects threats, contextualizes experiences, and regulates autonomic responses to create the rich tapestry of human emotion.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>

  <model id="cognition">
    <title>Cognition Model</title>
    <url>/cognition</url>
    <description>
      <paragraph>The Cognition Model focuses on the higher-order mental processes that enable us to perceive, think, and remember. Centered on the Cerebral Cortex—specifically the prefrontal, parietal, temporal, and occipital lobes—this model represents the mind as an advanced information processing system.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The simulation explores key cognitive frameworks such as Information Processing, Dual Process Theory (System 1 vs. System 2), and Cognitive Load. It visualizes how the brain integrates sensory data, manages working memory, and executes complex decision-making processes, emphasizing the fundamental link between cortical architecture and intellectual function.</paragraph>
    </description>
  </model>
</models>
